A Guide to the Papers of Rev. Mr. George Freeman Bragg, 1882-1925
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Papers of Rev. Mr. George Freeman Bragg, 1882-1925
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1942-18
The Bragg papers are made up of some business correspondence, writings and copies of the Afro-American Churchman and The Church Advocate.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Reverend Mr. George Freeman Bragg was born in Warrenton, North Carolina on January 23, 1863 to George Freeman Bragg Sr., and Mary Bragg. Mr. Bragg's parents moved to Petersburg, Virginia when he was an infant. George was reared in Petersburg and attended school at The St. Stephens Normal School and The Bishop Payne Divinity School in Petersburg, Virginia where he studied theology. In 1887 George Freeman was appointed deacon and in 1888 appointed a priest. While pastoring Bragg built a church and rectory for the St. James First African Church in Baltimore, Maryland. Rev Bragg increased the membership of the church from thirty to nearly a hundred. At the age of 19 Bragg published the first " Colored" newspaper The Lancet. The Lancet was designed to be an organ of reform in Virginia and the Rev Mr. Bragg was an ardent supporter of William Mahone and the Readjuster Party. Mr. Bragg became the first African American Page in the Virginia Legislator. He also published two other newspapers The Church Advocate and the Afro-American Churchman. Rev Mr. Bragg published his own newspapers and books with his own press and he taught typesetting to his sons. The Rev Mr. Bragg became widely known for his championing of civil rights and leadership in a wide array of community service. In 1887 Mr. Bragg married Nellie Hill.
Scope and Content Information
In the Afro-American Churchman and The Church Advocate, The Rev Mr. Bragg provides the only record of the development of the black Episcopal Church in America. The Newspapers are unique and reflect the current political and social views of the African American Episcopal Church at that time. Here one may find articles written by some of the leading African Americans of the time. Topics about the "Negro Problem", Liberia, and "Jim Crowism," are some of the issues addressed.
Organization
SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1912-1925
Mostly consisting of correspondence regarding church matters and social issues.
SERIES II: WRITINGS, 1916, n.d.
A number of writings, some may have been presented as speeches. The topics address religious and social issues. Included in this series is a pamphlet published by Bragg entitled Richard Allen and Absodom Jones. Included in this collection are also a number of books.
SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS
Two Photos of George Freeman Bragg
SERIES IV. PRINTED MATERIALS
A. Broadside, Programs
Two items: Broadside Concerns a social outing in 1899 the program; a conference in Norfolk, Virginia ca 1888.
B. Newspapers
George Freeman Bragg edited and published at least three newspapers during his lifetime. His first newspaper was published in Petersburg, Virginia from 1882-1886 and was titled the Lanceted. The Rev. Mr. Bragg relocated to Baltimore, Maryland and there he published both The African American Churchman beginning in 1886 and the Church Advocate in 1891- 1917.
Contents List
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE 1912-1925
  Mostly consisting of correspondence regarding church matters and social issues.
- SERIES II. WRITINGS 1916, n.d.
  - Writings: Biographical Sketch n.d. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Writings: The people & the politicians n.d. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Writings 1916 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Writings: St. Philips Church, New York n.d. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Writings: The Maryland Home n.d. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Writings: Untitled n.d. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Writings: Bishop Holly's Letter n.d. (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Writings: Untitled n.d. (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Writings: "Who Went About Doing Good" (Acts x:38) n.d. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Writings: The Anglican Episcopate and the Race Question n.d. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Writings: "By Faith We Work and Walk" n.d. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Writings: The Religious Life n.d. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Writings: Untitled n.d. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Writings: St. James, Portsmouth, Va, St. James, Tampa n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Writings: The Matter of Christian Leadership n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Writings: What We Can Do: Professor Charles H. Boyer n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Writings: In the South, and Elsewhere n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Writings: Liberty & Death n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Writings: A Work of Loving Nature n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Writings: A Filed Secretary The Standing Need n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Writings: The Reason Why n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Writings: Voluntary Ecclesiastical Segregation n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Writings: Maryland Home for Friendless Colored Children n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Writings: Secretarial Leadership Necessary for a Conversation of Our Energies n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Writings: Nothing could be more reasonable n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Writings: In the Letter, and In the Spirit n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Writings: "In Deep Rooted Tendency" n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Writings: The Force of Love n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Writings: Rt. Rev. Father in God n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Writings: The Work among Colored People n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Writings: The Real Trouble in the Race Question n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Writings: An Unanswered Prayer n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Writings: The One Thing I Do n.d. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Writings: An Old Maryland Plan n.d. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Writings: The Brave Report of the Episcopal Church in the South n.d. (Box-folder 1:11)
- SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS (Box-folder 1:12)
  2 photographs of Georgre Freeman Bragg
- SERIES IV. PRINTED MATERIALS
  - A. Broadside 1899 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - B. Newspapers n.d. (Box-folder 1:13)
    - The Church Advocate, Vol. XX #1
    - The Church Advocate, Vol. XXI #11[12] Nov 1910-Oct 1912
    - The Church Advocate, Vol. XXIII #1
    - The Church Advocate, Vol. XXV #3 Nov 1914-Jan 1917
    - The Church Advocate, Vol. XXV #4
    - The Church Advocate, Vol. XXVI #1 Feb 1917-Nov 1917
    - The Church Advocate, Vol. XXIX #3
    - The Church Advocate, Vol. XXXI #2 Jan 1921-Dec 1923